David mss., 1996-2008 LMC 2605
Lilly Library
David mss.
1996-2008
Lilly Library
David, Alfred, 1929-
LMC 2605
1 Box 1 standard
The David mss., circa 1996–2005, consists of the papers of professor Alfred David, 1929-2014.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Gift: 2008
Biographical Note
Alfred David, 1929-2014, was a professor at Indiana University. He was born in Hamburg, Germany, and his family moved to Houston, Texas in 1938. He earned his doctorate in English literature from Harvard University. He began teaching Chaucer and medieval English literature at Indiana University in 1958, and he retired from teaching in 1994. David also served as president of the New Chaucer Society and editor of the medieval section of the Norton Anthology of English Literature.
Scope and Content Note
The David mss., from 1996-2008, consists of papers of Indiana University Professor Alfred David concerning his vetting of Seamus Heaney's translation of Beowulf. The collection includes correspondence between David and Heaney, as well as other professors and editors such as Julia Reidhead and Mike Abrams, consisting of emails, faxes, and written and typed letters. It also includes various drafts by Seamus Heaney of Beowulf containing annotations and edits from Alfred David concerning the translation.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series: I. Correspondence and II. Beowulf.
Literature--translating; College teachers; Publishers and publishing; Indiana University -- Faculty; Heaney, Seamus, 1939-2013; David, Alfred, 1929-; Reidhead, Julia
- Correspondence, 1996-2008 (Box 1)
  - 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1999, 1.0 Folders (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - 2000 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 2008 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Undated/unfinished (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Beowulf (Box 2)
  - Early Draft Annotations Pages 34-98 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Early Draft Annotations Pages 7-93 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Early Beowulf Introduction Draft (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Full Beowulf Early Draft (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Unfinished Beowulf Drafts (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Later Draft Annotations Pages 33-85 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Later Draft Annotations Pages 45-80 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Later Draft Annotations 35-94 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Later Draft, Final Revisions Pages 44-93 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - First Draft with Marginal Corrections by Al David (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Heaney's First Proof (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Comments and Corrected Galleys (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - News and Reviews (Box 2, Folder 23)